I often see people online use the phrase
explain like I'm five when they want a
simple explanation of a complicated
topic they might want an explanation of
how planes can fly or how GPS Works
explained in a simple way even a
5-year-old could understand a little
while ago I came across a post that
wanted an explain like I'm five style
explanation for mathematical objects
called Spinners the post only got one
response and and it started with I don't
think Spinners are something that can be
explained like your five Spinners are
mathematical objects that come up in
advanced quantum physics and they have a
reputation for being pretty confusing if
you've learned any particle physics you
might know that all fundamental
particles can be broken up into two
categories the bons which Loosely
speaking are the force carrying
particles and Fons which are the matter
type partic parles that make up atoms
all known fundamental bons have either
spin one which are represented by
vectors or have spin zero which are
represented by scalers vectors and
scalers are familiar mathematical
objects to any undergraduate physics
student however all known fundamental
Fons have spin one half and these are
represented by Spinners so around half
of all known fundamental particles are
described by Spinners but what exactly
does that mean a first introduction to
Spinners will normally explain them in
terms of how they transform ukian
vectors are basically just pointed
sticks arrows and when we turn them
around
360° they end up back where they started
but when we turn Spinners around
360° they come back to the negative
version of themselves it requires two
full turns or
720° to get a spinner back to where it
started the property of requiring two
full turns to get back to the starting
position is one of the defining
properties of spinners and this is
demonstrated by drax's belt trick if we
turn the free end of this belt once we
get a Twist that cannot be removed by
translating the free end around however
after a second turn we can remove the
Twist by moving the free end like this
a similar trick can be done by holding a
cup or a plate one turn leaves your arm
with a Twist and a second turn gets you
back to where you
started now these are cute tricks but
when I started seriously learning the
mathematics of spinners I found most
textbooks were incredibly hard to follow
and I was left confused and
frustrated I've spent over a year
studying Spinners and at this point I
think I have the basics down my goal now
is to make a video series that lays out
the basics of spinners at a level
appropriate for undergraduate students
or early graduate students so that they
don't have to waste as much time being
confused like I
did like most complicated topics I think
it's best to learn Spinners in stages as
if you're climbing the stairs on a
staircase starting with the easiest and
most basic explanation and gradually
getting more complicated and
Abstract my planned staircase has five
steps basic examples of spinners in
physics viewing Spinners as the square
roots of vectors viewing Spinners as
members of Clifford algebras viewing
Spinners in terms of Le groups and Lee
algebras and finally talking a bit about
how Spinners are used to describe all
spin 1/ half particles in particle
physics and Quantum field
Theory so for the rest of this video I'm
going to give an overview of the steps
in this staircase you probably won't
understand a lot of what I'm going to
say but right now I'm just trying to
give you a basic road map of the ideas
that will come up later in this series
I'll dig into the details as the video
series goes
on so a good place to start learning
Spinners are examples from physics such
as basic Quantum spin States and the
polarization of light
waves in in introductory quantum
mechanics we learn that putting
electrically neutral silver atoms
through a magnetic field forces them to
choose between one of two states either
spin up or spin
down in physical space up and down point
in opposite directions 180° apart but
the quantum spin up and spin down states
of a particle don't live in physical
space instead they live in an abstract
State space
the rules of quantum mechanics tell us
that when two states are mutually
exclusive they must be
orthogonal the spin up and spin down
states of a particle are mutually
exclusive and so they are orthogonal
separated by
90° so here we see there's an angle
doubling relationship between these two
spaces a 90° turn in the abstract State
space corresponds to a 100 180° turn in
physical space this means that doing a
full turn in the state space corresponds
to two full turns in physical space
requiring two full turns to get back to
where we started is exactly what we
would expect from Spinners and so matter
particles are best described using
Spinners we can write a spinner as a two
component column where the two
components indicate the probabilities
for measuring SP spin up or spin down
from a given Quantum
State another example of spinners comes
from classical physics where light is
described as a wave the orientation of
this wave is called its
polarization two basic types of
polarization are vertical polarization
and horizontal
polarization if we take a vertically
polarized wave and rotate it 90° it
becomes horizontally polarized
after another 90° rotation it becomes
vertically polarized again although with
its phase shifted by half a
cycle again we have an angle doubling
relationship between physical space and
the polarization State space a half turn
in physical space corresponds to a full
turn in the polarization State
space while this is not the exact same
as our example with Quantum spin States
it does turn out that we can describe
polarization states of light using
Spinners once again we can write the
spinner as a two component column where
the two components indicate the amounts
of vertically and horizontally polarized
waves inside a given light
wave it's worth noting that this is a
purely classical effect with no quantum
mechanics at all Spinners are just
mathematical objects and while they are
very important in quantum mechanics they
can be used to describe things in
classical physics 2 now that we have
some motivation from physics the next
step is to discuss Spinners from a
purely mathematical point of view here
we learn that Spinners are like the
square roots of vectors this means that
we can take a 3D vector and use a
special trick to factor it into a column
spinner and a row spinner with a matrix
which is a rank two tensor we can
sometimes Factor The Matrix into a
column vector and a row Vector which are
both rank one tensors so we can factor a
rank two tensor into a pair of rank one
tensors now if we have a vector in 3D
space with components XY Z we can use a
special trick to write it as a 2X two
Matrix called a poly Vector this is done
by multiplying each component of the
vector by the sigma
matrices we can then Factor this 2x2
poly Vector into a column spinner and a
row spinner called poly
Spinners so loosely speaking we're
factoring a vector which is a rank one
tensor into a pair of spinners which are
sort of like rank 1/2
tensor now when we rotate a 3D Vector we
usually use a 3X3 rotation Matrix like
this but when we rewrite our 3D Vector
as a 2X two poly vector rotating the X Y
and Zed components is instead done with
a pair of rotation matrices one on each
side each Matrix is responsible for half
of the
rotation if we then Factor our poly
Vector into a pair of poly Spinners
notice that each spinner only gets one
rotation Matrix so each spinner only
rotates half as much as the vector does
just like we saw with Quantum spin state
and polarization states of
light so when looking at all the
different ranks of tensors we can think
of spinners as fitting in right here a
spinner is sort of like a tensor of rank
1/2 because we can combine two spinners
into a rank one tensor and because
Spinners transform half as much as
vectors
do while poly Spinners are associated
with rotations in 3D space in special
relativity it's Al possible to get
Spinners associated with
four-dimensional SpaceTime which are
called vial Spinners this is a bit
confusing as poly Spinners and vile
Spinners are different kinds of objects
but they both look like two component
columns we'll clear up the difference
between them in future
videos the next step in the staircase is
Clifford algebras Clifford algebras are
a bit abstract but they help help us to
find Spinners in any Dimension not just
three or four
dimensions most physics students are
familiar with scalers and vectors but
sometimes in physics it's more useful to
use their higher dimensional analoges by
vectors Tri vectors and so on for
example it's much more natural to
represent angular momentum using a b
Vector which is an oriented plane
instead of using a vector which requires
the awkward right hand rule to make
sense of we can build these by vectors
using the wedge product the wedge
product of vectors u and v is a plane
formed by the vectors u and v with an
orientation that follows the arrows if
we swap the order of the vectors we get
the same plane but with the opposite
orientation these are called B vectors
and they're a much more straightforward
way of representing
rotations with the wedge product we can
build bi vectors Tri vectors and the
other higher dimensional multiv vectors
which make it easier to represent
geometric ideas in physics without
having to rely on vectors for
everything an algebra with the wedge
product is called a grasman algebra or
sometimes an exterior
algebra when an algebra has both a wedge
product and a DOT product we call it a
Clifford algebra also called a geometric
algebra the Clifford product of two
vectors is like a combination of the dot
product and the wedge
product in the Clifford algebra for 3D
space the basis vectors are the sigmas
we saw before and in 4D space time the
basis vectors are the
gamas in Clifford algebras vectors are
also rotated using double-sided
transformations just as we saw with poly
vectors Spinners also arise naturally in
Clifford algebras for free here we can
see the spin up and spin down States
from quantum mechanics represented in a
Clifford
algebra we'll see that Spinners can be
defined as members of minimal left
ideals in Clifford
algebras this is a pretty abstract
sounding definition but we'll approach
it slowly over several videos step by
step app ultimately this is just a set
of instructions for writing down
Spinners using the right combination of
scalers vectors and bi vectors and it
works in any
Dimension now while being able to Define
Spinners in any Dimension is nice when
it comes to physics the most important
Spinners are associated with
three-dimensional space and
four-dimensional SpaceTime the poly
Spinners and vile
Spinners in in particle physics each
type of particle has its own spin value
with all known fundamental particles
being either spin zero spin 1/2 or spin
one composite particles can have higher
spin like spin 3 over2 and the
theoretical graviton has spin to any
theory of quantum mechanics that
incorporates relativity will require us
to understand how different particle
types transform under a change of
reference frame
to understand this we need to learn the
theory of Le groups and Lee
algebras if we exponentiate this 3x3
Matrix here times Theta we get a
rotation Matrix in the XY plane we say
that this rotation Matrix is part of the
Le group SO3 and this Matrix we
exponentiate is called a generator and
is part of the Lee algebra
SO3 there are generators for all the 3x3
rotation
matrices and the generators follow
special commutation relations which is
why they form a Lee
algebra if we use these commutation
relations as a starting point we can
find many generator matrices of all
different sizes that satisfy them when
we exponentiate these generators we get
rotation matrices for all the different
particle spin types the 3X3 matrices
rotate the standard 3D vectors the 2x
two matrices rotate poly Spinners and
all the other matrices rotate particles
with other spins so looking at the
different matrices that come out of this
Lee algebra gives us a recipe for
rotating particles with different spins
in three
dimensions we can follow similar
reasoning for Lorent transformations in
special relativity with the Le group
so13
which has six generators and this tells
us how to transform vile Spinners and
particles of other spins according to
Loren
Transformations at this point we'll have
most of the math required for
understanding Spinners so we'll look at
how they are used in particle physics
modern particle physics treats particles
as excitations in various fields for
example an electron is an excitation in
the electron field and a photon is an
excitation in the photon field the spin
zero higs field is a scalar field the
spin one force carrying particles are
each Vector fields and the various spin
1 half matter particles each have
spinner Fields the study of these fields
is called Quantum field Theory or
qft and the interactions between these
various fields are modeled by an
enormous formula called the standard
model
lran any terms in this formula that
contain a pair of fields represent an
interaction between those fields for
example this term represents the
electron spinner field interacting with
the photon Vector
field Spinners in Quantum field Theory
are four component columns called dra
Spinners which are really a pair of two
component vial spinners one having
left-handed chirality and the other
having right-handed
chirality ordinary tensors only have two
index types upper and lower but because
vile Spinners come in both left-handed
and right-handed versions they require
four index types using dots for
right-handed Spinners and no dots for
left-handed Spinners this notation is
called the Vander Warden
notation one interesting fact is that
the weak nuclear force is only known to
interact with left-handed particles so
reflecting the universe in a mirror or
equivalently swapping the left and
right-handed particles in the formula
does not result in the same physics and
studying Quantum field Theory will help
us understand how the various forces
like the weak Force interact with the
various spinner matter
particles the study of quantum f field
Theory can last several semesters in
graduate school so in this series I'll
only be scratching the surface of how
Spinners are used in
it so I realize if you've never studied
Spinners before everything I just said
was a lot to take in you don't need to
understand any of it now I'm just trying
to give you a basic road map for where
this video series is going I also don't
expect everyone to finish every single
video in the series some people might
have their curiosity satisfied after the
first couple steps and decide they don't
need to watch anymore and that's fine
but I'm hoping that anyone who wants to
learn about Spinners in any level of
detail will find this video series
helpful in untangling a rather confusing
Topic in physics so if you're interested
in watching more I've left a link to the
playlist in the description and we'll
start with learning some basic examples
of how Spinners are used in physics